Peter Buitenhuis fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Peter Buitenhuis fonds
1955 - 2005
F-242
Q104446968
88 cm of textual records 2 photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Physical description: 2 photographs located in F-242-3-1-10
Buitenhuis, Peter
Peter Martinus Buitenhuis (1925-2004), English professor emeritus at Simon Fraser University (SFU), was a prolific scholarly writer and literary critic. His academic career—which included teaching positions at Yale University, University of Toronto, McGill University, and University of California at Berkeley—saw the production of numerous books, articles, and reviews, including works on Henry James, E.J. Pratt, and Hugh MacLennan. Buitenhuis also conducted research and wrote on various topics pertaining to propaganda and World Wars I and II.
Of Dutch ancestry, Buitenhuis was born in Ilford Essex, England on December 8, 1925. He married three times and had seven children. With his first wife, Patricia (nee White), he had three children, Paul, Penelope, and Pym; with his second wife, Elspeth Fisher (nee Cameron), he had two children, Beatrix and Hugo; and with his third wife, Ann Cowan (nee Stephenson), he had two children, Juliana and Adrian.
In December 1943, Buitenhuis left his job as a bank clerk and enlisted in the Royal Navy. From 1943-1946, he was commissioned to several different ships, including the H.M.S. Beehive, where he served as a Navigating Officer in Coastal Forces, conducting anti-submarine and minesweeping duties in the English Channel and North Sea (1944-1945). After his time on the Beehive, Buitenhuis spent a short period in the Admiralty. In 1946, he was appointed as a navigational officer on H.M.S. Starling, where he served until his release from the Navy later that year. Buitenhuis received the 1939-45 Star, the France and Germany Star, and the Victory Medal.
Buitenhuis left the Navy to attend Jesus College at Oxford University on a veteran’s grant (1946). There he earned a BA and an MA in English language and literature. In Buitenhuis’s last year of studies, a professor from the University of Oklahoma (U of O) recruited him to teach English, thus enticing Buitenhuis to immigrate to the United States.
Buitenhuis taught at the U of O until 1951, at which time he left his position in response to an investigation by an Oklahoma legislature committee. The committee was putting pressure on the university’s employees to sign a loyalty oath to the constitution of the United States and to the constitution of Oklahoma State. Buitenhuis, neither interested in staying in Oklahoma nor signing the oath, went on to Yale University to pursue a PhD in American Studies, where he wrote his thesis on Henry James. After completing his degree, Buitenhuis stayed on at Yale’s American Studies Department to teach (1955-1959).
In 1959, Buitenhuis left Yale and immigrated to Canada, after receiving an invitation from Northrop Frye—then the chairman of the English Department at Victoria College in the University of Toronto—to teach at the College. He became a Canadian citizen c.1960, while still retaining his British citizenship.
While at Victoria College, in 1963, Buitenhuis joined with fellow Americanists from other Canadian universities to form the first American Studies association in Canada, the Canadian Association of American Studies.
Buitenhuis worked at the College as an associate professor until 1966, when he took a year to teach at the University of California (Berkley) as a visiting professor. In 1967, Buitenhuis returned to Canada to take a position at McGill University in Montreal. After several years at McGill, in 1975, Buitenhuis accepted the position of Chairman of the Department of English at Simon Fraser University (1975-1981) and moved to Vancouver.
Buitenhuis remained at SFU until his retirement in 1992. In that time, he not only taught in the Department of English, but was also the Associate Director in SFU’s Centre for Canadian Studies (1987-1988). He continued to teach literature well after his retirement through SFU’s Continuing Studies Department, and was still teaching until shortly before his death. Buitenhuis passed away on November 28, 2004.
Buitenhuis remained an active scholar, book reviewer, and writer throughout his life. Included in his many literature reviews and scholarly articles are several books, including E.J. Pratt and His Works; Five American Moderns: Mary McCarthy, Stephen Crane, J.D. Salinger, Eugene O’Neill, and H.L. Mencken; The Grasping Imagination: The American Writings of Henry James; The Great War of Words: British, American, and Canadian Propaganda and Fiction, 1914-1933; and The House of Seven Gables: Severing Family and Colonial Ties. Buitenhuis also completed a manuscript just weeks before his death titled, Empires of the Mind: British Authors' Roles in World War II.
Buitenhuis’s literary and academic career brought him into contact with many well-known authors, including Margaret Atwood, Northrop Frye, Timothy Findley, Thomas Wolfe, and Scott Symons.
published
Full
Published
Title is based on the name of of the fonds creator.
Fonds consists of records relating to the personal and academic life of Peter M. Buitenhuis. Activities, topics, and events documented include course planning and instruction; academic conference attendance and presentations; Buitenhuis's research, writing, and publications; his social life and relationships; and his death and memorial.
Records include correspondence; research notes; class and lecture notes; lesson plans, course syllabi, reading lists, and course work; photographs; manuscripts, publications, literary reviews, articles, and newspaper clippings.
The material was arranged by the archivist into series based on the personal and professional activities of Peter Buitenhuis.
Cowan, Ann; World War; Photographic materials; Textual records; Family and personal life; Education; Arts and culture
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by Buitenhuis's widow, Ann Cowan, in 2010.
As of December 2010 all accessioned materials have been processed. No further accruals are expected.
Peter M. Buitenhuis's records were in his custody until his death in 2004. His widow, Ann Cowan, maintained custody of the records until she donated them to Simon Fraser University Archives in 2010.
Most of the files in the fonds are open with no restrictions. However, some files may contain personal student information and access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy. Also, some original materials have been removed from files and replaced by photcopies. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available for each series.
- Teaching records, 1955 - 1996; F-242-1; 17 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records made and/or received by Peter Buitenhuis in the course of his teaching career. Topics and activities covered include course instruction and planning, program development, and Buitenhuis’s teaching positions and sabbaticals. The records reflect Buitenhuis's work at such institutions as University of California Berkeley, Yale University, McGill University, and Simon Fraser University's Department of English.
  Records include exams; course readings, notes, outlines, and class materials; student assignments; a thesis; program proposals; Master of Publishing Steering Committee minutes; and correspondence.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged chronologically.
  Yale University; University of California; Department of English; McGill University
  Some files may contain personal student information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  - [Yale University commencement program], 1955; F-242-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - California Berkley, 1965 - 1966; F-242-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - McGill correspondence, 1967 - 1975; F-242-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
    Pending review
  - Germany, 1978 - 1980; F-242-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Berlin, 1979 - 1991; F-242-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - English 356, 1981 - 1987; F-242-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Legal writing, 1985; F-242-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - English 491-2, 1985; F-242-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - English 808, 1986; F-242-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Harris, Lydia, 1987 - 1996; F-242-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - English 803, 1990; F-242-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Legal writing, 1990 - 1995; F-242-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Canadian Studies 210, 1991 - 1993; F-242-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Legal writing, 1992; F-242-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Master of Publishing program, 1993; F-242-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Yale admissions, 1993; F-242-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 242-1)
  - Canadian Studies 210, 1993 - 1996; F-242-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - Greg Lainsbury, 1993 - 1996; F-242-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - Publishing studies, 1995; F-242-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - Fiction of War, 1996; F-242-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
- Conference, presentation, and literary jury materials, 1978 - 2001; F-242-2; 8 cm of textual records
  Series includes materials relating to conferences, workshops, and literary juries in which Peter Buitenhuis participated, organized, or presented. Topics and activities documented include his participation on the Governor General Awards non-fiction jury, Canadian Association of American Studies conferences, a World War seminar in Paris, and a History of the Book Conference.
  This series includes correspondence, presentation papers, conference programs and pamphlets, newsletters, and submitted papers and presentation proposals.
  Governor General Awards; Canadian Association of American Studies
  The records are open with no restrictions.
  - Governor General Awards - non-fiction jury, 1978 - 1981; F-242-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - European Association for American Studies (EAAS) Conference - Rome 1984, 1983 - 1984; F-242-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - [International Writers' Meeting - Yugoslavia], 1984; F-242-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - [Canadian Association of American Studies (CAAS) Conference, 1991], F-242-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - Canadian Association of American Studies (CAAS) Pacific Rim Conference 1991, 1991 - 1992; F-242-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - [World War Seminar - Paris], 1998; F-242-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - History of the Book Conference, 2001; F-242-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
- Literary records, 1955 - 2004; F-242-3; 34 cm of textual records 2 photographs
  Series consists of records relating to Peter Buitenhuis's writing and publications. For types of records, see sub-series descriptions.
  The arrangement for the series and sub-series was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged chronologically within each sub-series.
  - Literary records - general, 1955 - 2004; F-242-3-1; 26 cm of textual records 2 photographs; Physical description: 2 photographs located in F-242-3-1-10
    Sub-series consists of records relating to Peter Buitenhuis's writing and publications, including a copy of his dissertation on Henry James (with associated review committee notes); correspondence with his book printer; drafts of his published works; research notes; drafts of an interview he conducted with Timothy Findley; photographs of Jack Hodgins; and an unpublished manuscript titled Empires of the Mind: British Authors' Roles in World War II.
    Materials include correspondence, research notes, literary drafts, manuscripts, photographs, a journal, and a notebook.
    Two photographs of Jack Hodgins are contained in file F-242-3-1-0-10.
    Findley, Timothy; Hodgins, Jack; James, Henry
    - Dissertation, The American Henry James, vol. 1, 1955; F-242-3-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - Dissertation, The American Henry James, vol. 2, 1955; F-242-3-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - [Notebook], 1961; F-242-3-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - Roger Ascham Press, 1968 - 1981; F-242-3-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - Henry James American portfolio, 1978 - 1984; F-242-3-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - Oxford Companion to Canadian Literature, 1981 - 1982; F-242-3-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - Timothy Findley interview, vol. 2, 1988; F-242-3-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - ["Waiting for the Christening": Canadian Authors and Propaganda in the Second World War], [199-]; F-242-3-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - World War II propaganda sources, 1991 - 1992; F-242-3-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - Germany after World War II, 1995; F-242-3-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - [Half a Century Ago, oxford reminiscence], [ca 1998]; F-242-3-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Bibliography, 1998 - 1999; F-242-3-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Motherhood Perverted, [ca 2001]; F-242-3-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - France 2003, 2002 - 2003; F-242-3-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Bibliography for writers and World War II], [ca 2003]; F-242-3-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 1, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 2, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 3, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-20 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 4, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-21 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 5, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-22 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 6, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-23 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 7, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-24 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 8, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-25 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 9, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-26 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors in World War II, draft], vol. 10, [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-27 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Jack Hodgins, [ca 1991]; F-242-3-1-0-10 (Archival box - small 242-8)
      Photographic materials
    - Timothy Findley interview, vol. 1, 1988; F-242-3-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 242-3)
    - [Empires of the Mind: British Authors' Roles in World War II - Manuscript], [before 2004] - 2004; F-242-3-1-0-28 (Archival box - standard 242-2)
  - Literary records - literature reviews, 1961 - 1997; F-242-3-2; 8 cm of textual records
    Sub-series includes records relating to numerous literary reviews written by Peter Buitenhuis for various scholarly publications, as well as news sources, such as the New York Times and the Globe and Mail.
    Records consist of newspaper clippings, correspondence, and manuscripts.
    Globe and Mail; New York Times
    - Reviews 1977-1978, 1961 - 1980; F-242-3-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews 1965: New York Times, 1964 - 1965; F-242-3-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews 1965: Globe and Mail, 1965 - 1966; F-242-3-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews 1970, F-242-3-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews 1971, F-242-3-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews, 1972 - 1973; F-242-3-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews 1972, 1972 - 1977; F-242-3-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews 1974, 1973 - 1975; F-242-3-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 242-4)
    - Reviews, 1976 - 1997; F-242-3-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
    - Reviews 1980, 1980 - 1983; F-242-3-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
    - Reviews 1981, 1981 - 1982; F-242-3-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
    - Reviews 1982, 1982 - 1985; F-242-3-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
    - [Reviews 1983], F-242-3-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
    - Reviews 1992, 1992 - 1996; F-242-3-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
    - Reviews 1993, 1992 - 1997; F-242-3-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
- Correspondence and personal records, 1956 - 2005; F-242-4; 17 cm of textual records
  Series includes correspondence between Peter Buitenhuis and various friends, colleagues, and peers—including Margaret Atwood, Timothy "Tiff" Findley, Northrop Frye, Thomas Wolfe, Adrienne Clarkson, Norman Holmes Pearson, Glynn Beard, Earle Birney, Anne Cameron, Joy Kogawa, Nigel Nicolson, Peter Such, Derek Martinus, Richard Stern, Betty Lambert, and Scott Symons (see files F-242-4-0-0-1 "Correspondence", F-242-4-0-0-2 "Correspondence: II L-Z," vol 1, and F-242-4-0-0-13 Scott Symons--please note that some original documents have been removed from the files and replaced with photocopies). Series also includes records relating to Buitenhuis's personal affairs, including financial records; party arrangements; church activities; and advocacy interests and involvement. Topics documented include the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC) program "Ideas," publications and manuscripts by Buitenhuis as well as other authors, Ford Maddox Ford, the Public Lending Right Commission, West Coast Energy, and Park Royal Shopping Centre.
  Records primarily consist of correspondence, but also include forms, a notebook, brochures, and reports.
  Atwood, Margaret; Beard, Glynn; Birney, Earle; Cameron, Anne; Clarkson, Adrienne; Findley, Timothy; Frye, Northrop; Kogawa, Joy; Martinus, Derek; Nicolson, Nigel; Pearson, Norman Holmes; Stern, Richard; Such, Peter; Symons, Scott; Wolfe, Thomas; Park Royal Shopping Centre; West Coast Energy Inc.; Canadian Broadcasting Corporation; Public Lending Right Commission; Ford, Ford Maddox; Lambert, Betty
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Also, some original materials have been removed from files and replaced by photcopies. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  - Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC) Ideas - World War I, 1978; F-242-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Correspondence, 1956 - 1995; F-242-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
    Restricted in part
  - Correspondence: II L-Z, vol. 1, 1959 - 1979; F-242-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Correspondence: II L-Z, vol. 2, 1959 - 1979; F-242-4-0-0-3
  - Parties, vol. 1, 1968 - [ca 1973]; F-242-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Parties, vol. 2, 1968 - [ca 1973]; F-242-4-0-0-5
  - House, 1970 - 1973; F-242-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Income tax Quebec, 1972 - 1989; F-242-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Canadian Association of Chairmen of English (CACE), 1978; F-242-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Glassco, David - Ford Madox (FM) Ford, 1982; F-242-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Perosa, Sergio, 1982; F-242-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Royal Navy, 1985; F-242-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - [Scott Symons], 1986; F-242-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 242-5)
  - Municipal affairs, 1986 - 1990; F-242-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - small 242-9)
  - [Correspondence], 1987 - 1998; F-242-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - small 242-9)
  - Public Lending Right Commission, 1987 - 1998; F-242-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - small 242-9)
  - [St. Monica's Church], 1996 - 1997; F-242-4-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - [Activism - Westcoast Energy and Park Royal], 1997 - 1998; F-242-4-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - [Obituaries, memorial programs, and notes], 2004 - 2005; F-242-4-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - [Memorial guestbook], 2005; F-242-4-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
- Publications, 1958 - 2001; F-242-5; 4 cm of textual records
  Series consists primarily of published books, articles, and literary reviews by Buitenhuis, on a variety of topics, including E.J. Pratt, Henry James, American Studies, World War propaganda, and writers during the World Wars. The series also includes two small files containing published reviews of works written and/or edited by Buitenhuis.
  The content of the following files is directly related to the listed items:
  F-242-5-0-0-1 and F-242-item15
  F-242-5-0-0-2 and F-242-item24
  Pratt, Edwin John Dove; James, Henry; American Studies
  - "Southwestern—Northeastern: Another Look at American Higher Education." The Educational Forum, 465-472., May 1958; F-242-5-0-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "Comic Pastoral: Henry James's 'The Europeans.'" University of Toronto Quarterly 31, no. 2, 152-163., January 1962; F-242-5-0-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "Henry James and Daudet." Humanities Association Bulletin 12, no. 2 (Winter), 62-69., 1962; F-242-5-0-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "'The Fresh Start and the Broken Link': Henry James's Ivory Tower." University of Toronto Quarterly 33, no. 4, 355-368., July 1964; F-242-5-0-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "Arthur Miller: The Fall from the Bridge." Canadian Association of American Studies (CAAS) Bulletin 3, no. 1 (Spring-Summer), 55-71., 1967; F-242-5-0-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "Arthur Miller: The Fall from the Bridge." Canadian Association of American Studies (CAAS) Bulletin 3, no. 1 (Spring-Summer), 55-71 [Annotated]., 1967; F-242-5-0-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - Five American Moderns: Mary McCarthy, Stephen Crane, J.D. Salinger, Eugene O'Neill, and H.L. Mencken. Toronto: Roger Ascham Press., 1968; F-242-5-0-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "The Return of the Novelist: Henry James's The American Scene." Canadian Association of American Studies (CAAS) Bulletin 4, no. 1 (Spring-Summer)., 1969; F-242-5-0-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "A Corresponding Fabric: The Urban World of Saul Bellow." Costerus offprint volume, 13-35., [197-?] - 1970; F-242-5-0-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "American Studies in Canada." American Studies: An International Newsletter 10, no. 1 (Autumn), 19-24., 1971; F-242-5-0-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "Two Solitudes Revisited: Hugh MacLennan and Leonard Cohen." The Literary Half-Yearly 13, no. 2, 19-32., July 1972; F-242-5-0-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 242-6)
  - "Writers at War: Propaganda and Fiction in the Great War." University of Toronto Quarterly 55, no. 4 (Summer), 277-294., 1976; F-242-5-0-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 242-6)